Mss.Ms.Coll.200
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Letter to John K. Kane, Attorney General, Harrisburg, Feb. 18, 1845; 10x8; Pennsylvania Institution for the Instruction of the Blind. Finance committee
    Philadelphia, L.S.: Sam[ue]l Breck and F[rederick] Fraley. 1p.and add.and enc.of 2p. Forwards financial statement of the institution. Originally bound with pamphlet vol.1067.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", Feb. 24, 1845; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874
    A.L.S. Concerns the politics of the Caledonian Railway bill.
  - Letter to [Felix Edouard] Guerin de Menneville [sic], Paris, March 3, 1845; 10-1/2x8; Bonaparte, Charles Lucian, 1803-1857
    Florence, A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. His work. Concerning Guerin Meneville's proposed trip to Italy.
  - Note to S. S. Bowerbank, April 2, 1845; Sowerby, James de Carle, 1787-1871
    A.N.S. 1p.
  - Letter to "Sir", April 6, 1845; Davis, John Edward, 1815-1877
    A.L.S. Concerns coloring of prits for "Flora Antarctica". Mentions being an officer in the Antarctic Expedition. Mentions Hooker and Percival Meggs.
  - Letter to [sir] R[oderick] I[mpey] Murchison, April 7, 1845; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867
    A.L.S. 1p. Wishes to borrow fine native gold, platinum and malachite for his lectures.
  - G[eroge] Bancroft to ----, June 23, 1845; 4 1/2" x 7"; Bancroft, George, 1800-1891
    Washington, 1 p. and endorsement. 3d.per.N. Unsigned. Encloses (book?) received from Mr. Joseph Hume, M. P.
  - Letter to William Smyth, Cambridge, July 18, 1845; 10x8; Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866
    Cambridge, Mass., A.L.S. 1p. Introduces Benjamin A. Gould.
  - Letter to Charles B. Trego, Aug. 2, 1845; 11x8-1/2; Kirkbride, Thomas Story, 1809-1883
    Typed L. 1p. Copy. Offers his experience to the state to aid in hospitals for the insane. Presented by W.J.Bell,Jr.;July 18,1962. From originals at Institute of Penna. Hospital.
  - Letter to Hardouin Michelin, Paris, September 10, 1845; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Neuchatel, A.L.S. 2p., add. In French. Expresses his thanks for the specimens sent to him. Refers to Diekmann and Desor.
  - Letter to P[arker] Cleaveland, Sept. 18, 1845; 8 3/4" x 7 3/4"; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Pertains to some plants he wishes sent; mentions Loudon's Encyclopaedia.
  - Letter to [Hugh Blair Grigsby ??], Dec. 23, 1845; 8" x 10"; Ward, Townsend, 1817?-1885
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. Mutilated. Probable sale of the library of the Philosophical society. [This letter was found by Mrs. W.S. Morton among other letters of the Hon. Hugh Blair Grisby, Char lotte co. and Norfolk, Virginia.]
  - Letter to ----, Dec. 28, 1845; Buckland, William, 1784-1856
    A.L.S. 2p.and end. Has not replied since he has just moved into the house of Oxford, and all of the fossils are in a closet.
  - Address [to mechanic's institute], [1845-1846]; Rankine, William John Macquorn, 1820-1872
    A.D. 21p. Discusses state of contemporary science; mentions Franklin, Galileo, the steam engine, railroads, electric telegraphs, photography, agriculture and the value of technical training.
  - Letter to C[harles] Edwards Lester, Jan. 4, 1846; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Peale, Rembrandt, 1778-1860
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. and add. As the oldest living artist in America, will contribute a portrait and biographical material for Lester's proposed work [Artists of America, 1846?].
  - Letter to [René Joachim Henri] Dutrochet, Feb. 12, 1846; 8x5; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895
    New Haven, Conn., A.L.S. 1p. Presents publication. Located in: 593:D19s. J.D.Dana. Structure and Classification of Zoophytes.
  - Letter to Eliza and Helen Edmonstrone, Madeira, Feb. 13, 1846; Waterton, Charles, 1782-1865
    Walton Hall. A.L.S. 3p. and add. Mentions renovations made at Walton Hall. Speaks of local affairs and acquaintances.
  - Letter to Cha[rle]s B. Trego, Feb. 23, 1846; 11x8-1/2; Kirkbride, Thomas Story, 1809-1883
    Typed L. 2p. Copy. Concerning state support for an insane hospital, and his hospital for the insane. Presented by W.J.Bell,Jr.,July 18,1962. From originals at Institute of Penna. Hospital.
  - Letter to Charles B. Trego, Harrisburg, Feb. 27, 1846; 11x8-1/2; Kirkbride, Thomas Story, 1809-1883
    Typed L. 1p. Copy. Concerning his hospital for the insane. Presented by W.J.Bell,Jr.;July 18,1962. From originals at Institute of Penna. Hospital.
  - Letter to J. C. Jay, Feb. 27, 1846; 10" x 8"; Lea, Isaac, 1792-1886
    Phila., A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. Seal. Pressing personal affairs give him little time for scientific pursuits. Publication of his paper on the Unio in the [APS] Transactions. Presented by Seymour Adelman, Dec. 1952.
  - Letter to Eliza Edmonstone, Madeira, Mar. 12, 15, 1846; Waterton, Charles, 1782-1865
    Walton Hall. A.L.S. 2p. and add. Summoned before the magistrates concerning the poaching business. Mentions the renovations made at Walton Hall. Speaks of local affairs and acquaintances.
  - Letter to Helen Edmonstone, Madeira, [March 15, 1846]; Waterton, Charles, 1782-1865
    Walton Hall, Saturday night. A.L.S. 1p. and add. Mentions the renovations made at Walton Hall. Speaks of local affairs and acquaintances. On same page as Charles Waterton to Eliza Edmonstone; Mar. 12, 15, 1846.
  - Letter to Henry Darwin Rogers, March 31, 1846; Silliman, Benjamin, Jr., 1816-1885
    New Haven. A.L.S. 1p. Hopes he, Binney and the others will everything organized for the meeting. Will publish his paper in 20 days.
  - Letter to Dr. [John] Lindley, March, 1846; Chambers, Robert, 1802-1871
    A.L. 3p.
  - Letter to [Sir Richard] Owen, April 3, 1846; Kaup
    Darmstadt, A.L.S. 3p. Praises Owen's proposal for a national collection of fossils. Mentions the British Museum and the College of Surgeons. Also refers to Falconer and Cuvier.
  - Letter to Charles B. Trego, Philadelphia, April 9, 1846; 10x8; Dupuy, John
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. Concerning the coal trade in Philadelphia.
  - Letter to "My dear Madam", May 14, 1846; 9" x 7 1/4"; Waterton, Charles, 1782-1865
    Walton hall, A.L.S. 1p. Birds studied during his travels with the Misses Edmonstone. News of friends.
  - Letter to Messrs. Lea & Blanchard, May 28, 1846; 7 1/2" x 10"; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. Relative to loan of Mr. Hale's volume on Indian languages west of the Rocky mountains.
  - Notice of latitude and longitude, and request that the note be returned to the Coast Survey, July 21, 1846; 5-1/4x10-1/4; Bache, George Mifflin, 1811-1846
    D.S. 1p.and end.telling location where found. Presented by Mrs. Elizabeth Du Bois Bache, New Rochelle, Conn.; Aug. 4, 1964.
  - Letter to W. R. Davy, Oct. 3, 1846; Ansted, D. T. (David Thomas), 1814-1880
    A.L.S. 4p. Recommends Johnson's book on chemistry in agriculture. His own work on agriculture is geological.
  - Letter to [William] Gaskill, Dec. 21, 1846; Buckland, William, 1784-1856
    A.L.S. 2p. Spending of funds in Westminster which are collected by the Deanery.
  - Letter to Miss Louisa Cheatham, 1846-1847; 11x8-1/2; Cheatham, Benjamin Franklin, 1820-1886
    Typed L. 4 items (3 Letters and 1 journal) on 14 leaves. Copies. Pertaining to the Mexican War. Presented by Mrs. Sioussat; Dec. 1961.
  - Letter to Messrs. Carey and Hart, Philadelphia, Feb. 5, 1847; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Boston. A.L.S. 1p. and add. Wants copies of his works for geologists and naturalists. Wants them sent, "care of Dr. A. A. Gould," and will return what they order.
  - John Cadwalader to Charles B. Trego, February 15, 1847; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Cadwalader, John, 1805-1879
    Philadelphia, 3 pp. and endorsement. A.L.S. Mistake in Mr. Fernon's resolution concerning the purchase of the site of the Elm Tree Treaty of William Penn with the Indians.
  - Letter to Geo[rge] P. Bond, June 30, 1847; 8" x 10"; Keely, George W.
    Waterville, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Inquires about chronometer he ordered. Presented by Gilbert Chinard and Edwin P. Meiners, Jan. 1945.
  - Letter to ---, March 31, 1847; Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, Isidore, 1805-1861
    Museum d'Histoire Naturelle, Paris. A.L.S. 4p. Thanking his correspondent for a gift to the Museum's collection and at the same time offering him a collection of birds, mainly from the African Interior, for his studies. He hope to benefit other collections in other countries as far as he can, and at the same time gives a list of desiderata for his own musuem, including some American animals, insectivores, nests, etc. St. Hilaire refers to his hopes of exchanges of wanted objects between his museum and the Washington Institute [Smithsonian?].
  - Letter to [Michael] Faraday, May 7, 1847; Croker, John Wilson, 1780-1857
    Kingston, A.L.S. 4p. Variation in temperatures on thermometers due, probably, to plates on which they were attached.
  - Minutes and report of By-Laws Committee, June 1, July 6, 1847; 10x7-3/4 and 12-3/4x7-3/4; Provident Trust Company of Philadelphia
    D.S.: Benjamin Matthias and Charles B. Trego. 2p.and end.
  - Letter to Professor Simon Greenleaf, June 2, 1847; Hitchcock, Edward, 1793-1864
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Has been unable to reply, having retreated to the South from the winter, but thanks for volumes on legal evidence and the Evangelists, which he has deposited in the College Library.
  - Letter to F.W. Porter, June 29, 1847; Copway, George
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning Chippeway education efforts.
  - Letter to "Monsieur", Aug. 15, 1847; Schultz, Carl Heinrich, 1798-1871
    Berlin. A.L.S. 1p. in French. Presents copy of work "Nouveau Systeme de Morphologie des plantes," hopes for mention in British journals. Discusses previous work.
  - Letter to [David Milne-Home], Sept. 7, 1847; Chambers, Robert, 1802-1871
    A.L.S. 3p. and end. Asks him to send copy of his article to Darwin. Is still unhappy about the geological conclusions of Glenroy.
  - Letter to Aug[ustus] A. Gould, Sept. 29, 1847; 10x7-1/2; Leidy, Joseph, 1823-1891
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.,end. Inquires of work by Dr. Binney. Asks for specimens of Helix.
  - Letter to W. C. Bond & son, Oct. 11, 1847; 8" x 10"; Keely, George W.
    Waterville, Me., A.L.S. 1p. and add. Returns the chronometer. Presented by Gilbert Chinard and Edwin P. Meiners, Jan. 1945.
  - Note to "Dear Sir", Aug. 15, 1847; Auckland, George Eden, Earl of, 1784-1849
    A.N.S. 1p. Invitation to dine and to meet Mr. Brooke.
  - Letter to F[rancis] O. J. Smith, Nov. 2, 1847; 9-1/4x5-1/2; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885
    New Haven, Conn., A.L.S. 3p. Concerning the telegraph, and electricity.
  - Letter to "Sir", November 9, 1847; Carpenter, William Benjamin, 1813-1885
    A.L.S. 4p., enc. wanting. Acknowledges a request of the Russell Institution to present a series of lectures on the revelations of the microscope. Mentions the Marylebone Institution and Islington Institution.
  - Letter to Alfred A. Carter, Nov. 22, 1847; 8x5; Breck, Samuel, 1771-1862
    A.L.S. 1p.and end. Forwards autographs for his collection.
  - Letters patent issued to Richard Albert Tilghman for his improvement in decomposing potash feldspar for obtaining certain salts, Dec. 4, 1847; 14 1/2" x 20"; United States. Patent and Trademark Office
    Washington, Parchment D.S: James Buchanan, Secretary of state;Edmund Burke, Commissioner of patents; Richard Albert Tilghman. 3 leaves. Seal.
  - Letter to C.R. Weld, Jan. 8, 1848; 7 1/4" x 4 1/2"; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867
    R[oyal] Institution, A.L.S. 1p. Faraday's views regarding honors, particularly those conferred by his own country. Printed and reproduced: Journal of chemical education. V.26,1949,p.441 - Duveen.
  - Letter to Ebenzer Meriam, June 12, 1848
  - Letter to [James Scott] Bowerbank, June 23, 1848; De La Beche, Henry T., (Henry Thomas), 1796-1855
    Geol. Survey Office. A.L.S. 3p. Had conversation with Prof. Owen. Work important; should be continued. Owen's request necessitates consult (?); suggests Wednesday next.
  - Letter to "My Dear Sir", Aug. 5, 1848 (?); Buckland, William, 1784-1856
    A.L.S. 1p. Encloses something [wanting] from the Bishop of Norwich.
  - Letter to François Arago, Paris, Aug. 19, 1848; 9x7-1/2; Muirhead, James Patrick, 1813-1898
    Birmingham, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Concerning legacy from Watts. Muirhead received Watts' copies of the publications of the Academie des sciences.
  - Letter to Tho[ma]s E. Blackwell, Sept. 15, 1848; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Brunell(?)
    L.S. 3p.and end. Describes a plough used at Dover which he thinks will be superseded by a steam dredger. Sketches the plough.
  - Letter to James Rush, Oct. 1, 1848; 5" x 7 3/4"; Rush, William, 1801-1864
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Re Pt. 7 of their father's biography containing the notice of the signers of the Declaration of independence.
  - Lettet to Charles Wilkes, Oct. 3, 1848; Dana, James D. (James Dwight), 1813-1895
    A.L.S. 1p. Is working on the geological report and the marine crustacea.
  - Letter to Monsig. Lavimo Medici Spada, Rome,Italy, Oct. 28, 1848; Shepard, C. U. (Charles Upham), 1804-1886
    New Haven, A.L.S. 2p.,add.,end. Incomplete. Lists minerals. States his big collection is now housed at Amhurst College.
  - Letter to "Sir", January 15, 1849; Lankester, Edwin, 1814-1874
    A.L.S. 1p., end. Requests his correspondent to transmit his subscriptions to the Ray Society as early as convenient.
  - Letter to Mr. Murray, April 21, 1849; 7x4-1/2; De La Beche, Henry T. (Henry Thomas), 1796-1855
    A.L.in 3rd.P. 1p. Thanks for permission to make a woodcut from an illustration.
  - Letter to "My Dear Sir", May 10, 1849; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874
    A.L.S. 2p. end. Mentions family and friends.
  - Schedule 3.-Persons who died during the year..., June 1, 1849- June 1, 1850; 18x13; Pennsylvania. Springfield Township, Bucks County
    Printed broadside filled in in ms. and S: Samuel B. Thatcher. 1p. and end.
  - Letter to George Livermore, Aug. 17, 1849; 10x8; Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866
    Cambridge, Mass., A.L.S. 1p. Asks him to forward a reprint of his article on the New England Primer to E. D. Ingraham.
  - Letter to [John?] Percy, Sept. 7, 1849; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867
    A.L.S. 1p. Introduces Dr. Gustav Magnus (i.e. Heinrich Gustav), professor of Natural Philosophy at the University of Berlin, who intends to attend meeting at Brimingham. is "very pleasant man and talks good english." Mentions Phillips.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", Sept. 11, 1849; Magnus, Gustav, 1802-1870
  - Letter to "My dear Sir" [David T. Ansted?], Dec. 8, 1849; Henslow, J. S. (John Stevens), 1796-1861
    A.L.S. 2p. Hopes he will come to the meeting. Sedgwick Forbes and Owen will be there.
  - Letter to Isidore Geoffroy St. Hilaire, Paris, December 31, 1849; Bonaparte, Charles Lucian, 1803-1857
    Leyden, A.L.S. 2p., add. In French.
  - Letter to "Sir", March 2, 1850; A.L.S. 2p. end. Concerns serch for John Bartram's correspondence by Dr. Darlington. Also Collinson's papers.; Dillwyn, Lewis Weston, 1778-1855
  - Letter to [Charles] Waterton, April 29, 1850; Lindley, John, 1799-1865
    A.L.S. 3p. Congratulates Waterton on the "retreat of Mr. Simpson." Informs Waterton Where he will be on Friday.
  - Letter to Th[omas William] Parsons, May 10, 1850; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. Wished to discuss geological chart in resuit in Albany, but guests will prevent the discussion. George Hillard visits.
  - Answers to interrogatories of commissioner in the case of Blanchard vs. Kimball., June 3, 1850; 8 1/4" x 10 3/4"; Trego, Charles B., 1794-1874
    Affirmed before James Devereux, Esq., Commissioner, [Philadelphia], 8 pp. and endorsement. D. Unsigned. In re differences between Blanchard's and Kimball's cutting machines.
  - Letter to G.A. Jahn, Aug. 28, 1850; Gilliss, J. M. (James Melville), 1811-1865
    Photo. of A.L.S. 1p. and add. From original in Diederich Collection, University of Amsterdam Library.
  - The Oriental Society, Oct. 1, 1850; 10x8; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865
    D.S.: Edward Everett, Charles Beck and William W. Greenough. 4p. Refers to John Pickering and their study of oriental languages.
  - Schedule 4.-Productions of agriculture..., October 3, 1850; 18x13; Pennsylvania. Springfield Township, Bucks County
    Printed broadside filled in in ms. and S: Samuel B. Thatcher. 4p.
  - Letter to [Henri] Milne-Edwards, Paris, Oct. 29, 1850; Carpenter, William Benjamin, 1813-1885
    London. A.L.S. 11p. Concerning echinoidea and orbitoides and limestone in Australia. Foraminifera and refers to David Forbes.
  - Letter to S[amuel] P[ickworth] Woodward, Nov. 17, 1850; Hancock, Albany, 1806-1873
    Newcastle on Tyne, A.L.S. 8p. Concerns the structure of mollusks. Mentions Gray, Owen, Edwards, Johnston and Clarke.
  - Letter to ----, Dec. 5, 1850; 7 1/4" x 4 1/2"; Sedgwick, Adam, 1785-1873
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. Busy schedule of commitments. Wishes success to the Literary gazette.
    Not Found: 1/24/2011
  - Letter to G[eorge] Ransome, Dec. 17, 1850; Sabine, Edward, Sir, 1788-1883
    A.L.S. 1p. Cannot attend their meeting, for must be at the Royal Society.
  - Letter to the Duke of Argyll, [Dec., 1850]; Brewster, Sir David
    A.L.S. 3p.and end. Concerning an exhibition. Refers to Cumming.
  - Letter to William [Falconer], 1850; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Falconer, Thomas, 1805-1882
    Friday, A.L.S.with initials. 4p. Concerning a Sir James Falconer. Once slept on floor during a snow-storm, with Fillmore. Comments on a publication.
  - Letter to Rev. Robert Ainslie, Jan. 15, 1851 and Nov. 28. [1850?]; Lubbock, J. W., (John William), 1803-1865
    2 A.L.S. 4p. Discusses parliamentary legislation regarding building of railway lines; need for finacial backing and attendance at meetings. Mentions Lords Camden and Holmes.
  - Letter to Col. [Thomas] Aspinwall, London, Jan. 25, 1851; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864
    A.L.S. 1p. end. Encloses letter [wanting] to Professor Pliny Miles, an American living in England whose present address Schoolcraft does not know.
  - Tho[mas] Corwin to Charles B. Trego, January 27, 1851; 7 7/8" x 9 7/8"; Corwin, Thomas, 1794-1865
    Treasury Department, [Washington, D. C.], 1 p. A.L.S. Appointing Mr. Trego a commissioner of the United States mint.
  - Letter to John H. Jenks, Boston, Feb. 14, 1851; 10" x 7 3/4"; Audubon, Victor Gifford, 1809-1860
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Will send the 8th no. of the Quadrupeds, and Yarrell's Birds.
  - Letter to John H. Jenks, Boston, Feb. 17, 1851; 10" x 7 3/4"; Audubon, Victor Gifford, 1809-1860
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Terms for publication [of Quadrapeds ?].
  - Letter to Edmund Bailey O'Callaghan, March 1, 1851
    A.L.S. 4p. Concerns voyages of Thevet and Canada. Histor and nomenclature of pumpkin and squash. Mentions Baukin, Condolle, Linneaus and Magnus.
  - Letter to his brother [ Bailey], March 9, 1851; 5" x 8"; Bailey, Jacob Whitman, 1811-1857
    West Point, A.L.S. 2p. and end. Believes he is entitled to a land grant for his services in the two Indian wars. Presented by Whitman Bailey, March 1948.
  - John Tatlock to ----, Williams College, March 29, 1851; 6 3/4" x 8 5/8"; Tatlock, John
    Mass., 1 P. A.L.S. Regarding package to be sent to Williams College.
  - Letter to G[eorge] C[linton] Swallow, April 1, 1851; 10x7-3/4; Cleaveland, Parker, 1780-1858
    Brunswick, A.L.S. 2p.and end. Concerning botanical collection made by J.S.Henslow and wishes to give Henslow some Maine specimens. Hopes they can get together to arrange the Maine items for shipping to England.
  - Letter to J[ames] Jerwood, April 15, 1851; Plumptre, Charles, 1818-1887
    A.L.S. 2p. Admiration and thanks for a paper on the planet Neptune.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", April 17, 1851; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864
    A.L.S. 1p. Presents copy of his "Bibliographical Catalogue."
  - Letter to Messrs. Munroe & co., April 17, 1851; 8" x 10"; Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866
    Cambridge A.L.S. 1p. Relative to the publication of a certain book.
  - Letter to Messrs Smith & Funston, July 3, 1851; 10x7-1/2; Cattell, Abraham Gilmore & Co.
    Philadelphia, L. 1p. Reports on shipment of wheat which arrived in bad condition. Presented by Mrs. W.J.Robbins; June 30, 1964.
  - Letter to [Henri] Milne-Edwards, Paris, July 23, 1851; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873
    Cambridge, Mass., A.L.S. 3p. and add.,end. In French. Concerning publication by Robin and his comments on marine biology (gastropods, etc.)
  - Letter to Mrs. Fanny [Lucy F. Hall] Whiteman, Cincinnati, Ohio, Sept. 10, 1851; 10x8; Posey, John F.
    Walnut Spring, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Delighted that she is happily married. Has sent money. Family news. Presented by Mrs. Dorothea K. Jenne, April 1967.
  - Letter to John Bohlen, Phila., Oct. 27, 1851; Darlington, William, 1782-1863
    A.L.S. 2p. Concerns prints of Linneaus, Hooker, Collinson and De Condolle. Mentions Miss Collinson and Dr. Booth.
  - Letter to T[itian] R[amsay] Peale, Nov. 7, 1851; 8x5; National Institute for the Promotion of Science
    Washington, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: L.D.Gale. 1p.and add. Notifies him of a social meetint to be held.
  - Letter to Sir John Ross, Dec. 26, 1851; Brewster, Sir David
    A.L.S. 3p and end. Wants log of "Felix". Thinks the Admirality should have retained him on the Committee of Offices.
  - Copy of Pennsylvania act of 1851 relative to incorporation of the Lebanon Valley Railroad and to taxing property formerly exempt from taxation, 6x8; Pennsylvania. General Assembly
  - Letter to the editor of the "Union", ca. 1851-1855
    Newby, et al. A.L.S. 3p. Authors feel that Thomas M. Howe (Member, U.S. House of Reps., 1851-1855), should focus more attention on bridges and aquaducts in Pittsburgh; no action should be taken on Wheeling Bridge. Signed: John Lawrence Newby, Jacob G. Metcalf, Jas Cummins, S. Riss, J.S. Forbs.
  - Letter to J. Weinen, January 26, 1852; Lankester, Edwin, 1814-1874
    A.L.S. 2p. Informs his correspondent what dates Lankester can lecture and the costs involved.
  - Letter to Geo[rge] Smith, Upper Darby, Jan. 31, 1852; 10x8; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    Washington, Xerox copy of A.L.S. 1p. Thanks for meteorological observations from Delaware County Institute. Hopes they will publish flora and fauna of Delaware County and will help classify the animals. Presented by the Delaware County Institute of Sciences; Aug. 1967.
  - Letter to Samuel B. Buckley, Feb. 13, 1852; Dana, James D. (James Dwight), 1813-1895
    New Haven. A.L.S. 1p. Returns manuscript, since it cannot be put in the March number.
  - Letter to Edward Charlesworth, Museum, York, March 11, 1852; Waterton, Charles, 1782-1865
    Walton Hall, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Refuses membership in the Zoological Society of London. Concerning breeding of geese: birds in his park.
  - Report of select committee to whom were referred certain resolutions relative to a school of mines, April 20, 1852; 8 3/8" x 13 1/8"; University of Pennsylvania
    Philadelphia, 1 p. Pr.D.S.: J[oseph] R. Ingersoll, G[eorge] M. Wharton, T[obias] Wagner.
  - Letter to --, May 17, 1852; Bacquerel, Edmund, 1820-1891
    A.L.S. 3p. In French. Identifies rocks sent him. Analysis of water from the Dead Sea.
  - Letter to [William Barton?] Rogers, June 30, 1852; Olmsted, Denison,1791-1859.
    Yale College. A.L.S. 4p. His course of instruction in astronomy at Yale described. John C. Adams praises his College Astronomy.
  - Letter to Miss Percy, Sept. 29, 1852; Brewster, Sir David
    A.L.S. 1p. Concerns rainbows.
  - Letter to G. P. Peckam & Co., Oct. 11, 1852; Silliman, Benjamin, Jr., 1816-1885
    A.L.S. 1p. Gives them permission to use his name as an occasional contributor in a new Journal.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir" [David T. Ansted?], Nov. 25, 1852; Henslow, J. S. (John Stevens), 1796-1861
    Kew, A.L.S. 2p. Wishes him great success, and add's Gray's wishes.